Guide to the Sheridan Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sheridan papers
1787-1812
OSB MSS 29
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
The papers include correspondence, memoranda, speech drafts, copies of acts, and printed material relating to Sheridan's Parliamentary career. Materials on the union with Ireland and Catholic emancipation include a letter from John Milner, Bishop of Castabala; memoranda in Sheridan's hand; annotated copies of the proposed Disabilities Act of 1800 and of "The Substance of the Speech of the Marquis Wellesley"; and a survey of heads of Catholic religious communities in England. Sheridan's backing of the Prince Regent is documented in letters to George IV and Lord Holland; speeches and speech drafts; and papers relating to the refurbishing of Carlton House in the late 1780s, including inventories of new furniture.
Sheridan, Richard Brinsley, 1751-1816
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Sheridan Papers contain correspondence, manuscripts, speech drafts, printed material and other papers related to the Parliamentary career of Richard Brinsley Sheridan.
The substance of the speech of the Marquis Wellesley on the 31st January, 1812, in the House of Lords, on the motion of Earl Fitzwilliam, respecting the present state of Ireland; Catholic emancipation; Catholics -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Ireland; Irish question; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1789-1820; George, King of Great Britain, IV, 1762-1830; Grey, Charles Grey, Earl, 1764-1845; Holland, Henry Richard Vassall, Baron, 1773-1840; Milner, John, 1752-1826; Perceval, Spencer, 1762-1812; Sheridan, Richard Brinsley, 1751-1816; Wellesley, Richard Wellesley, Marquess, 1760-1842; Great Britain. Parliament; Carlton House (London, England); Catholic Church -- Great Britain
- Box and Folder List
  - "A Bill to Explain, Amend, and render more effectual, an Act ... to relieve [Roman Catholics] from certain Penalties and Disabilities", 1800 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder +)
    Scope and Contents
    Heavily revised and annotated by R. B. Sheridan. Printed proposal.
  - [George IV, King of Gt. Brit.], 1762-1830. Documents relating to the alteration and furnishing of Carlton House, 1787 May, 1790 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder +)
    Documents include an estimate, a petition, a resolution by the House of Commons, a royal order, letters (one by Henry Holland), and accounts. Nine pieces altogether, mostly copies.
    - George IV, King of Gt. Brit., 1762-1830. Letter (photostat, two copies) to an unnamed recipient, Windsor Castle, 1781 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder +)
      Signed "G. P." Wishes to explain his "apparent indifference" to her, since "nothing could be further from ye sentiments of my heart."
    - Grey, Charles Grey, 2d Earl, 1764-1845. Letter (copy) to the Prince of Wales, later George IV, 1811 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder +)
      Co-authored by Lord William Grenville, with a few holograph revisions by R. B. Sheridan. Express their concern over their treatment by the Prince and Sheridan during the Regency Crisis.
  - "Lines to the Lord Chancellor of Ceylon -- presented to His Lordship at Oatlands on the Duke of York's birthday August 16th 1807 by a brother labourer in the Vineyard.", 1807 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder +)
    Anonymous manuscript.
  - "A List of the Principals of the Religious Communities from Abroad, now resident in England, & their Answers to the Circular letter", 1800 Jun (Box 1, Folder +)
  - McMahon, John, col.
    - ALS to R. B. Sheridan, Carlton House, [n.y.] May 13 (Box 1, Folder +)
      About Sheridan's not having come to see the Prince Regent as expected.
    - ALS to [R. B. Sheridan], n.d. (Box 1, Folder +)
      To get Charles James Fox to recommend John William Ward Dudley's memorandum to Duke Francis Russell Bedford, for he rests his bar to Lord Moira's introduction of him to the Duke.
  - Milner, John, Bp. of Castabala, 1752-1826. ALS to R. B. Sheridan, Winchester, [1800] Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder +)
    Reviews the situation of Roman Catholics in England and the reasons for their opposition to the Catholic bill in Parliament.
  - Payne, John Willett, ca. 1752-1803. ALS to R. B. Sheridan, Carlton House, n.d. (Box 1, Folder +)
    About dinner with the Prince Regent.
  - Perceval, Spencer, 1762-1812. Letter (3d person, copy) to the Prince of Wales, later George IV, [n.p.], [1810 Dec,1811 Jan] (Box 1, Folder +)
    Copied by R. B. Sheridan. About the Regency Bill.
  - Sheridan, Richard Brinsley Butler, 1751-1816
    - AL (draft) to [General Lake], [n.p.], [1804?] (Box 1, Folder +)
      Printed in Cecil Price, The Letters of RBS, II, 214, # 503, with some differences. About the reversion of the grant of the Duchy of Cornwall, whereupon the Prince of Wales appointed Sheridan. Gerard Lake could not accept the office when he was outside the country.
    - AL (draft) to the Prince of Wales, later George IV, [n.p.], [1808 Jul 23] (Box 1, Folder +)
      Printed, in slightly different form, in Cecil Price, The Letters of RBS, III, 36, # 672. Apologizes and explains misunderstanding on "my vote on Ld William Wellesley-Pole Mornington business," the Catholic question, and the Spanish question.
    - Letter (copy) to [the Prince of Wales, later George IV], [Barnes-Green], [1810 Dec 9] (Box 1, Folder +)
      Variant copy, printed in Cecil Price, The Letters of RBS, III, 95, # 840. With a few pencilled marginalia in another hand. About an examination of King George III by his physicians being shown to the Privy Council, and the adjournment of Parliament.
    - Letter (draft copy) to Lord Henry Holland, [Queen Street], [1811 Jan 15] (Box 1, Folder +)
      Heavily revised by Sheridan. Printed in Cecil Price, The Letters of RBS, III, 100, # 744. Defends his treatment of Lords Grey and Grenville during the Regency crisis.
    - Memorandum, holograph, to the Prince of Wales, later George IV, [n.p.], 1812 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder +)
    - Holograph draft or copy of "By the King A Proclamation.", n.d. (Box 1, Folder +)
      A Proclamation by King George III.
    - Memorandum, holograph (Box 1, Folder +)
      Concerning the reliability of newspaper reports of an incident at Newmarket, involving the Prince of Wales and the Duke of Bedford.
    - Memoranda, holograph, on Irish and Catholic question (Box 1, Folder +)
    - [Speech in Parliament on the Regency], [1788 Dec 12, 1789 Feb 12] (Box 1, Folder +)
      About the order of succession in choosing a regent, Parliament's responsibilities, royal prerogatives, etc. Possibly written in preparation for Sheridan's speech of 1788 Dec 22. Anonymous manuscript.
  - "The Substance of the Speech of the Marquis Wellesley, on the 31st of January, 1812, in the House of Lords, on the Motion of Earl Fitzwilliam, respecting the Present State of Ireland.", 1812 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder +)
    Printed pamphlet. Heavily annotated by R. B. Sheridan, 8 p.
  - "Verses, which obtained in June last, the Prize of the Gold Medal, given by the Prince Regent to Winchester School. On the Retreat of the French from Santarem in Portugal", n.d. (Box 1, Folder +)
    Printed copy.